I recently read the book deep work by
author Cal Newport Cal defines deep work
as professional activities performed in
a state of distraction free
concentration that pushes your cognitive
abilities to their limit these efforts
create new value improve your skill and
are hard to replicate JK rowling use
deep work to complete the final book of
her Harry Potter series the deadly
hollows in 2007 she needed to escape the
distraction of screaming kids and
barking dogs so she checked into a suite
in a five-star hotel in downtown
Edinburgh Scotland she says I didn't
intend to stay there but the first days
writing went well so I kept coming back
and I ended up finishing the last of the
Harry Potter books here Bill Gates used
deep work in 1974 to program the first
version of basic in just eight weeks Cal
says that Gates worked with such
intensity for such lengths during the
two-month stretch that he would often
collapse into sleep on his keyboard in
the middle of writing a line of code he
would then sleep for an hour to wake up
and pick up right where he left off the
basic software that Gates wrote in eight
weeks well in a state of deep work
became the foundation of a billion
dollar company author Cal Newport an MIT
graduate and Georgetown professor claims
that deep work allowed him to double his
output of research papers while raising
a family writing this book and teaching
full-time at a prestigious university
the first two cases Gates and JK Rowling
might be extreme as most people don't
have the ability to go off the grid and
do deep work for weeks at a time but Cal
shows that we can maintain a busy
schedule and still find ways to do deep
work and produce significant results in
our lives that others find hard to
replicate but how exactly does deep work
lead to these best-selling books
innovative products and elite levels of
productivity while neuroscientists have
found that intense periods of focus in
isolated fields of work causes myelin to
develop in relevant areas of the brain
myelin is a white tissue that develops
around neurons and allows brain cells to
fire faster and cleaner so in a sense
when we practice deep
work we upgrade our brains and allow
specific brain circuits to fire more
effortlessly and effectively the brain
upgrade we get from deep work allows you
to rapidly connect ideas and uncover
creative solutions in today's economy
the ability to do deep work is
increasingly valuable an increasingly
rare it's valuable because when you
produce something great in our
hyper-connected world it has the ability
to spread to billions of people
producing something great is necessary
to stand out amongst the noise and avoid
being forgotten by the flood of
information that we deal with on a
day-to-day basis think of your last
tweet how long did it last how quickly
was it forgotten
deep work is becoming increasingly rare
because deep work requires undivided
attention and our world is being filled
with more and more tempting distractions
so the ability to do deep work is
becoming increasingly difficult
co-workers expect you to immediately
respond to an email or an instant
message employers want you to function
in an open office concept of constant
distraction your friends and followers
online expect you to maintain a social
media presence it's not enough to try to
ignore these distractions we are
hard-wired to be distracted and pay
attention to novelty in a 2012 study led
by psychologists Wilhelm Hofmann and Roy
Baumeister involving 205 adults found
that we are only able to resist
temptations to take a break from work to
check email surf the web or watch TV
just fifty percent of the time but there
is hope you can build a scale of deep
work and escape the trap of constant
distraction thus separating you from the
pack and making you indispensable in
today's economy here are three deep work
strategies that you can incorporate into
your schedule to heighten your ability
to focus and produce results that are
hard to replicate first schedule your
distraction periods at home and at work
most of us allow ourselves to go online
at any moment and check our phone
whenever buzzes or dings but doing so is
training your brain to avoid deep work a
day full of unscheduled distraction is
training your brain to give in to any
and all distractions to build your
tolerance to avoid distraction you need
to place boundaries on your distract
have a notepad nearby and put down the
next distraction break you'll have hold
your focus until that time at first it's
going to be painful but remember that
doing this is effectively doing the reps
that build your ability to concentrate
second develop a rhythmic deep work
ritual Cal says the easiest way to
consistently start deep work sessions is
to transform them into a simple regular
habit the goal in other words is to
generate a rhythm for this work that
removes the need for you to invest
energy in deciding if and when you're
going to go deep Cal uses several
examples in the book to show that
scheduling chunks of deep focus in an ad
hoc manner doesn't yield much
productivity at all for people who are
not seasoned at doing deep work it's
best for them to have a reoccurring time
each day or each week to go into deep
work early morning is typically the best
time to do this because at that time you
typically don't have to deal with
incoming requests the research shows
that people new to deep work can
typically only do it for about one hour
and masters of deep work can typically
only hold their attention up to four
hours in intervals between 60 and 90
minutes throughout the day so the
ultimate goal of each day is to plant
deep work rituals throughout the day
with the ultimate goal of building up
the some of your deep work practices to
four hours a day the third strategy to
cultivate deep work in your life is to
have a daily shutdown complete ritual
sleep is the price we need to pay in
order to do deep work it's the interest
we pay on the loans of intense focus
required to do deep work to ensure that
we get adequate sleep and restore our
attentional reserves for the following
day Cal recommends that we incorporate
an evening shutdown into our daily
routine an evening shutdown ritual
involves making a plan to complete any
unfinished tasks goals or projects the
following day getting a series of steps
lined out for the following day is
enough to get items off your mind so you
can disconnect for the rest of the day
when you get things off your mind you
restore the ability to sleep well and do
deep work the following day
after Cal completes his plan for the
following day he will say to himself
shutdown complete it's pretty cheesy but
he says it's a great cue to unplug in
the end deep work is incredibly valuable
because it changes your brain and allows
you to produce innovative work that is
hard to replicate that was the core
message that I gathered from Cal's great
book Cal does a great job of teaching
deep work rituals and reducing the fear
of leaving shallow work behind I highly
recommend this book for anyone looking
to make something meaningful in this
world if you would like a one-page PDF
summary that includes the steps needed
to build a deep work ritual just click
the link below and I'd be happy to email
it to you if you already subscribe to
the free productivity gain newsletter
this PDF is already in your inbox thanks
for watching