[Music]
uh the core idea i want to talk about
today
is the following question
is slow productivity
the solution
to burnout
so slow productivity is a emerging topic
of thought we've been talking about more
and more frequently
and i want to get into it with this core
idea
all right let's give some
background to where the concept of slow
productivity came from what motivated it
we are in a moment right now
in which there is a
popular and visible pushback against the
general notion of productivity
and by productivity i mean just the
general drive to try to get more things
done
now i think the coronavirus pandemic
helped amplify this but this movement
predates the coronavirus pandemic if
we're going to use books
as a rough proxy for cultural thinking
on this topic we can really look to 2019
february of 2019 when ginny odell
published how to do nothing
this book probably helped spark more
than anything else this
modern moment of anti-productivity
thinking
it was a popular book a new york times
bestseller
barack obama selected it as one of his
best books of the year
it opened the floodgates to multiple
other books along these same lines
so we got celeste headley's do nothing
that came out soon after
i actually interviewed celeste for a new
yorker piece this fall
got a little bit deeper into this we
also got devin price had a book called
laziness does not exist i blurbed that
book it was a good book helen ann
peterson had can't even
the
book length treatment of her viral
buzzfeed article about millennial
burnout uh more recently we have oliver
berkman had four thousand weeks which i
blurbed that book as well it's fantastic
that book's really been killing it so
there's been this long string of books
since 2019 that are all basically making
the same point
we're burnt out we're doing too much
we're tired of doing too much
i saw this anti-productivity movement
even among you my listeners and readers
in 2020 i wrote an essay from my
newsletter about this asking
is the term productivity
over
do we need something new
and it led to a really heated discussion
and two subsequent follow-up posts we
had a lot of back and forth discussion
on this in the spring of 2020 that made
it clear that there are a lot of you out
there
that are just exhausted
exhausted with activity and work
your life outside of work
and need something more than just
falling back on how do i get more done
all right so that is the the modern
anti-productivity movement
here's the issue
the question left unanswered in a lot of
this work
is what should we do about it
we all agree
these books are doing well because we
all feel
exhausted but the question is what
should we do about it and my
opinion here is that we haven't had a
lot of fully featured answers the
typical response that we will get to
what we should do about it is basically
just
do less and be okay about that
which is perfectly fine advice but is
not in itself i think a fully fledged
solution to this issue of burnout now we
get this advice from many different
angles some of those books i talked
about before come at this from an
economic materialist standpoint they say
well you're doing a lot of things
because essentially you're being
exploited by
the capitalist superstructure and so
it's an act of political resistance
to not do something do nothing as a as
an act of political resistance some of
these books are more cultural just we
have a cultural
a culture of overproduction
maybe it goes back to the protestant
work ethic or whatever
and we just need to defy that culture as
an arbitrary culture we should just do
less things
nothing wrong with that advice i just
don't think it's enough by itself to
actually cure what ails us
because we do like to do things
there's nothing that makes us more
consistently miserable as a species
than actually doing nothing for any
extended period of time it makes us very
uncomfortable it makes us feel
non-efficacious it makes us feel
rootless and bored and anxious we'd like
to do things the problem is not activity
the problem is too much activity so
we need a
more
sophisticated solution than simply
saying
it's okay to not do as many things just
do less
that maybe is a
step in the right direction but we need
to take many steps more this is what
brings me to my recent thinking on this
emerging concept of slow productivity
slow productivity is meant as a response
to this question of what should we do in
the face of being exhausted
by all that we have to do
so to look into this topic of slow
productivity i started by trying to
understand
what was productivity for our ancient
ancestors
in other words as human beings
what is natural
when it comes to activity
there's a basic question but we need an
answer to this question of what is
natural if we're going to try to get
back to something that's more
attuned to the human condition and so i
went back and did some work trying to
understand the rhythms of activity of
our paleolithic ancestors
we obviously don't have direct
observations about this but i ended up
talking to a quantitative anthropologist
from oxford university who is one of the
world's experts at studying extant
hunter-gatherer tribes in the
philippines and using robust methods to
try to try to measure
what their activity levels are like and
very carefully try to make some
extrapolations from this to other to our
hunter-gatherer past that's an
extrapolation you have to do carefully
but he's sensitive and careful about
that and here's basically what you see
our best guess
at what activity was like
for the bulk of our species existence is
you would be doing skilled and important
work
basically every day
mainly focused on food acquisition and
preparation as well as child rearing
but you would be uh you know these
extant tribes they studied if you were
gathering herbs
you had a huge expert understanding of
the various plants and their various
uses it's very expert work or if you're
hunting hunting was a very skilled
activity when you don't have very
sophisticated
weapons like rifles right so you're
doing skilled but important work
at a natural pace
this is definitely what they found in
their work on these tribes is there's
lots of breaks
you might be spending all day on a hunt
but there's going to be a two-hour part
in the middle of the day where you're
just resting and maybe you take there's
a nap over here there's a natural pace
with ups and downs of intensity and
never too many things at the same time
there's no notion of i have 18 things
i'm trying to get done
as a paleolithic hunter-gatherer and i'm
trying to go through this list it's like
we're doing this today and then that
right that's basically what we did
throughout most of our history
now compare that to where we are today
where we are today and let's focus
mainly on the world of work just to keep
this
more precise where we are today
is
maintaining lists of things that we need
to do obligations and commitment some of
them explicit some of them implicit that
are
massive
massive list of obligations and
commitments in the world of work these
just come flying at us through emails
they come flying at us through quick
requests during zoom meetings hey cal
can you take care of this or can you
jump on this flying at us in informal
conversations in the hallway where a
boss grabs you and says
look into this can you get this done for
me and we have these very large list of
things that are on our plate i call this
state chronic overload because we have
more things on our plate than we can
easily imagine how we're going to get
them done and this is a state that is
persistent we constantly have this
overloaded list of things that we have
to do
this causes three problems three
problems that we're not faced by our
paleolithic ancestors one is just the
simple short circuiting of the center of
our brain that is dedicated to making
long-term plans
goal completion
humans have a center in their brain that
does this very well even our close
primate relatives do not have anything
that's quite as powerful as our ability
to plan and go after goals this is
tapped into our motivational systems
we feel good when we make a plan we feel
even better when we execute the plan we
feel bad if we don't
this system gets completely overloaded
when you have 700 unread messages in
your inbox and 75 different projects
tasks and ongoing commitments that
you're trying to juggle it is too many
things for that part of your brain to
imagine how it's going to accomplish and
it short circuits that planning that
planning center of our brain that makes
us anxious that makes us miserable
again our paleolithic ancestors never
had 700 unread emails each of which
representing a commitment
that we can't wrap our mind around how
we ever gonna satisfy all these
commitments two
when you have way more things on your
plate than you can easily imagine
handling you suffer from what i think is
one of the more
insidious tortures of modern office work
which is the
overhead spiral
so if you give me something to do here's
a project
i want you to work with these two people
and get it done
there is a fixed amount of overhead
that comes with this project because we
have to kind of coordinate so there's
going to be i don't know some notion of
number of meetings we have to do to talk
things through and make a plan there'll
be some non-trivial number of emails we
have to send back and forth to get
questions answered or to move the
project forward
in isolation that's all fine if i'm
working on something yeah let's meet
about it once a week and send some
emails in between that's fine that's
just the overhead cost of working with
people to accomplish something no
problem the issue is what if we have 25
of these ongoing at the same time each
of them has the same fixed amount of
overhead each one needs that weekly
meeting each one needs a couple dozen
emails sent each week and it adds and
adds and ads until your schedule becomes
overloaded
with this fixed overhead
and now you are spending almost all of
your time
talking about the work you need to do
with no time left to actually execute
the work
again i think this is the knowledge
worker equivalent of chinese water
torture it is maddening it is deranging
we saw this really clearly amplified
during the first half year of the
chronovirus pandemic where office
workers had to suddenly work remote
shifting operations remote meant that
there was a lot of new work that got
generated right because we have to
figure out how do we do our work if
we're remote so suddenly everyone's
obligation list got bigger each of these
things brought with it a meeting and
some emails what happened
i heard report after report from
knowledge workers saying i am spending
eight straight hours per day in zoom
i would get complaints from people that
said my biggest issue is i don't know
when to use the bathroom during the day
i'm on zoom that often in zoom doing
email while in zoomed the entire day
this is a parody of work life where all
you're doing is talking about work not
just i have too many meetings all you
were doing was meetings that's overhead
spiral
personified right there so again you
have too many things on your plate that
you've committed to the overhead itself
takes over your whole schedule and
finally the last issue with chronic
overload is we it's relentless in its
pace there is never any time where you
get to relax there's never any time you
get to downshift
remember our paleolithic ancestors if
they're doing an all-day hunt
might have hours in there where they're
just sitting around yeah it's the heat
of the day
let's sit in the shade of a tree and
just like nap and chat
or we hunted the last two days it's kind
of rainy today not great conditions
we're not going to hunt today at all
in a system of modern work with chronic
overload where you always have way more
on your plate than you ever can get
around the handling there is a constant
pressure on execution because there's
always things that need to get it done
and you're always behind
so every day
you fill it relentless work every minute
you have available
probably have to do some evenings
probably have to do some weekends as
well to get around the overhead spirals
we're not wired for this relentless pace
of work where you never have any relief
and it's pegged at
this 10 on the scale of 1 to 10 of how
much how hard you're working day after
day after day after day
this i think is the more
detailed
socio-physiological explanation for what
all of those anti-productivity books
were commenting on this is why we're so
miserable chronic overload creates those
three problems those three problems
alienate us from the the rhythms of work
for which we're wired as people and that
is why we're not happy
that is then what we need to solve
how do we get rid of chronic overload
how do we get rid of those
issues that come from chronic overload
just saying i'm going to do less isn't
going to cut it
hey boss
i've decided i don't want to be a part
of the exploitative capitalist engine
so i'm not going to work today
good luck not going to solve it we need
we need a more detailed sophisticated uh
solution here it's not going to work to
say hey client
i do not want to be a
stooge in a a protestant work ethic
culture established during the
pre-colonial period uh in the early days
of migration to the united states so um
i'm not going to answer your email
that's not a solution we need something
more sophisticated all right slow
productivity is that answer
slow productivity is that answer
let me give you three quick ideas for
what slow productivity might mean three
elements to it this is going to evolve
but let's try to get something pinned
down here so to me there's three big
things i care about with a slow
productivity philosophy
doing fewer things
doing those things at a natural pace
obsessing over the quality of the things
you do
that definition of productivity a
productivity that prioritizes those
three things i think can get us back
towards
the rhythms of work for which we are
wired while also
fulfilling us doing interesting work
letting our companies grow
helping our
team succeed getting promotion still
getting the autonomy that comes from
getting good at things that are rare and
valuable that is compatible with that
so let me just touch on those three
things real quickly
do fewer things
i think your workload and ideal world
would be below that level of chronic
overload
you have few enough things that you are
committed to doing on your plate that
you are not suffering from the short
circuiting of your planning circuit
you're not suffering from overhead
spirals and you do not feel like you
have no
no
option but to have a relentless pace for
your feeling every minute of your day we
need to do many fewer things
and if you work for yourself if you're a
freelancer run your own company
aggressively titrate how many things you
take on at the same time
you are not a computer processor where
you want your
pipeline of
instructions to execute to be full so
you never miss a particular tick you're
a human
you're not wired to do that we need to
do many fewer things what if you work
for someone else
well i think we need to completely
rethink how work is assigned in the
workplace this should be transparent
how much work is this person doing
what's on their plate
so we can all see it and then we can
have very clear understandings of what
is reasonable
and if i see you know jesse has
a fair number of things on his plate i
can't put something else on it it's on
me to figure out something pops up it
needs to get done at some point i can't
just say jesse handle this i have to
figure out
where does this go
until someone has room for it it can't
just go on their plate the answer here
is probably going to be external systems
things that need to get done go into
external systems where they bring with
them the information they need to be
accomplished and have clear statuses and
priorities and then individuals pull
pull work out of the system as new slots
open
this might sound like it's a pain i
don't care if it's a pain
it's what we're wired to do keep my load
reasonable
and i'll pull in new stuff when i'm done
with what's on my plate don't just give
it all to me and say figure it out
you're going to short circuit my brain
you're going to make me miserable
all right second piece of slow
productivity work at a natural pace
we cannot just peg our efforts at a 10
for eight to nine hours a day
day after day week after week week after
week
this is not natural for humans we need
seasonality in our work first of all
seasonality meaning hard times balanced
by easier times and i think we should
have this
at all
scales so this week some days are harder
than others
i'm going to pull back on friday and
come into the weekend maybe a little bit
more relaxed but monday i'm pegging it
we should have
certain months
perhaps that are more intense than
others
this is an intense month we're kind of
getting after it but you know what in
june things really get quiet around here
and i'm pulling back and i'm going to
have very light days right so uh
seasonality at different levels maybe
even seasons like professors do
winter i'm getting after it summer i'm
pulled back far
rest recovery up down up down at all
scales
i think we absolutely need this the
other thing we have to do to get a more
natural pace to our work is adjust the
time scale at which we care about
accomplishment
instead of caring about how much do i
get done on the scale of days and weeks
you say i worry about what i get done on
the scale of months and years
completely changes your relationship to
the current moment when you want to
produce a good number of very high
quality things over the next three years
it really changes how you feel about
tuesday
now it's not so important that every
minute of tuesday you're getting after
it in fact you might say i need to take
a couple weeks off here so that i can
really have a high quality push for the
weeks that follow it completely changes
your relationship to work when you say i
don't care about how many things i check
off a list this week what i care about
is what is on my cv that i produce over
the last five years
that's much more compatible with
seasonality ups and downs the final
point here the final part of slow
productivity i mentioned was obsessed
about quality
if you're going to do less
you need to pair that with doing what
you do better
this will make the work more fulfilling
because you're building and applying
craft
remember our example of our paleolithic
ancestors skilled important activity
we get motivation for that
we don't get motivation for adjusting
the fonts in a powerpoint deck
for fundraising for some company idea we
probably shouldn't be doing in the first
place just because we're bored
but
crafting the computer program that's
going to run and do something really
cool and you can see it producing the
book the brilliant new marketing
campaign
so we want to focus on doing smaller
number things but doing those things
much better is going to feel more
fulfilling it is also what is going to
give you both the ability and the
courage to say no to other things
when your main metric becomes how do i
do what i do better
now it's easy to say i'm not going to do
this mid lean thing
i'm not going to do this distraction
i'm not going to jump on this call i'm
not going to learn this new plugin that
maybe will bring me some new email
subscribers for my news list because
that's not going to help me get better
at what i'm trying to do
it is much much easier to be minimalist
in your scheduling when you're focused
relentlessly on a small number of things
getting better and better at it it also
earns you the right to be more
autonomous
the better you get at what you do best
the more leeway you have to say i'm not
coming onto that committee i am not
going to
do this client contract it's barely
overlaps what i like to do it's going to
be
incredibly time consuming
i'm not going to have to do 25 social
media posts a day in some quixotic quest
to build up an influencer audience it
gives you the autonomy you need
to take control over what you spend your
time on and what you don't
so that is my answer that is my answer
to the anti-productivity movement yes we
are overloaded it's a problem why
because of chronic overload causes all
these issues that alienates us from our
human wiring what's the solution
not to discard productivity
and say do less and let's celebrate that
but to get more specific and say let's
redefine productivity
we'll call it slow productivity
and we're going to build this very
intentionally from the ground up to get
our work lives back aligned with our
ancient wiring
do fewer things
do this work at a natural pace
obsess over quality
that i believe is the proper response to
our current
rightly pointed out as problematic state
of overload
that is how we take back control of
activity in our life and keep it
fulfilling keep it meaningful keep
options open but also
get away from all of the issues we're
currently facing in our world of chronic
overload
all right so that's what i have on slow
productivity that's a new thought guys
so i'm sure it's going to evolve
uh
jesse you've heard me talk about this a
few times now did you just you've heard
i just listened to you talk about on the
ferris interview yesterday
that's right yeah so the day before
the day before this came out or a couple
days before my interview with the tim
ferriss came out and slow productivity
was one of the topics that we got into
i've also written about slow
productivity in for the new yorker so my
my last of my office based columns for
them which came out in early january was
on slow productivity uh and i may or may
not be working on a book proposal
on the topic so you might be wondering
why i'm talking about it
uh
i mean ironically for a book on slow
productivity it can't come out fast
i think that's the problem i was like
guys i stayed up every night for two
months and got this book done by just
relentlessly working as fast as possible
i think that's not gonna work
yeah you talked about this in the past
too in previous podcast episodes where
you said you were going to kind of walk
us through
the process of writing the book and
stuff so i'm looking forward to that
it's actually
already started yeah so maybe there's
some breaking news here so in in past
podcast episodes we were talking about
a book i'm working on a proposal on for
the deep life
this would be a second book
so i might be i'm working on potentially
the deep life and slow productivity in
some order
might be the next two books all right
none of that is inked you know none of
that's actually written down or signed
or none of it's official uh but that's
that's what i'm currently thinking is
those might be the next two books i
write and that's what you did before the
last two books right you worked on them
simultaneously yeah i like doing that um
because i want to just work i want to
think deeply and write
and so i sold
digital minimalism in a world without
email i sold those at the same time and
then that allowed me to just not worry
about selling books for four or five
years i could just write when i was done
with one book i knew what i was working
on i mean i'm gonna put my head down and
right type of guy that makes me happy
having to go out and talk about the
books you know okay that's harder for me
i like the part where it's just me
me and the idea i guess me and the idea
and jesse and tens of thousands of
podcast listeners but but that's it just
our small circle talking about these
things
um
so i like that i like to sell multiple
books at a time if i can because i don't
want to spend it's a pain to sell books
man and it's it's
it's stressful and it's complicated and
there's a ton of
fiddling overhead on it too i mean these
proposals are
50 pages long it just takes a long time
to write but it's not fun writing it's
not oh i'm writing about ideas it's you
know you're writing about your marketing
plan and stuff like that so yeah
i try not to do it more than i need to
one thing you mentioned the ferris
interview was he asked you started off
with your relationship or your
steve martin he was asking about him and
then you were talking about his
autobiography
i listened to the auto audio book
recently and at the end
he was he had the
the quote where he was in i think it was
in the jerk when he was like leaving the
house i was like i just need this and i
need this one thing and he needed all
those things that kind of reminded me of
what you just instead this and then just
this and just a little bit of that and
then just this and yeah
good book born standing up yeah i
recommend it
you