are you a list maker like do you wake up
in the morning and make lists and cross
things off and then decide what are the
key items on that list no I'm a Time
blocker time blocker yeah yeah so I'm
not a big believer in to-do list I like
to Grapple with the actual available
time like okay I have a meeting here I
have to like pick my kids up from school
here here's the actual hours of the day
that are free and where they fall all
right what do I want to do at that time
well okay now that I see that there's a
lot of gaps in the middle of the day
here they're short maybe there I'm going
to do lot of small non-c conly demanding
thing oh this first 90 minutes in the
morning is like the main time I have
uninterrupted okay so this I'm going to
work on writing so i' I've been a big
believer of this since I was an
undergrad like you give your time a job
as opposed to having a list which is
somewhat orthogonal to what's actually
happening in your day and then just as
you go through your day saying what do I
want to try to do next which I think is
a lot less
efficient I'm going to try your method
um I try and structure my days as much
as I can but it just never quite Works
um do work late into the night or you no
no I'm I'm a 5:30 man okay yeah so 5:30
p.m. that's it yeah more or less that's
my cut off now the the one exception is
um if I'm writing on Deadline I'll
sometimes like if I need to get more
writing done I can do uh an evening
writing session which which I got used
to through long experience of I used to
write my blog post at night after like
my kids went to bed now they're older
and they don't go to bed as early so
it's like the one thing I have left that
I'll do after 5:30 is like every once in
a while I'll do like a 90 minute evening
writing block um but I call this by the
way this whole philosophy I call fix
schedule productivity and I've been
doing it since I was a grad student fix
the work hour schedule that's my
commitment I work in these hours um and
then work Downstream from that for
everything else so like this controls
like even what you decide to bring into
your life because you know I can't go
past a schedule um and it drives you to
be more Innovative and how you deal with
your time and schedule you have to be
efficient because you only have these
these hours here uh that's been you know
a signal for my my since I was in my
early 20s fix the schedule and don't
work outside of that schedule now it's
your move to figure out anything you
want to do you have to make that work
you want to become a professor figure
out how to make that work you want to
write books while you're being a
professor figure out how to make that
work you don't have the option of just
throwing hours at it and you innovate a
lot I think when you have the
constraints where do sleep and exercise
fit into your schedule uh what's your
typical to bed time wakeup time what's
your um typical exercise routine and the
reason I ask about this is because I
think nowadays we hopefully people
understand that exercise and cognitive
function are are inextricably linked
yeah and we're all going to live longer
lives and be sharper mentally by doing
exercise yeah so I mean my main like
actual working with weights I do this
predinner right and this was an
innovation the last couple of years it's
it's a fantastic psychologically for me
this is a transition from work to like
family time after work so so I'll do
like 45 50 minutes uh garage God's gym
you know that we built during Co after
I'm done working before dinner and once
you get used to that like it also forces
you to like I got to finish work because
I got to get this in before dinner but
then I'll do also quite a bit of walking
if it's not a teaching day so I'm not on
campus uh I do a lot of thinking on foot
um you know walking my kids to the bus
stop which isn't particularly close in
back so I'll do a lot of walking but
that's when I my serious exercise now is
always always pre- dinner then uh I want
to be up you know in our room by 10:
yeah and then at that point I don't
track so I have insomnia issues which
which actually has been like key driver
of a lot of the things I think about
especially with slow productivity is I'm
very wary because I can without any
control on my own just find myself
unable to sleep sometimes fall asleep or
stay asleep fall asleep yeah I mean I
used to get it really bad um not so bad
now but you know it comes and goes that
really affected the way I thought about
productivity because it seemed like to
me the the definition of just I get
after it with a bunch of stuff
wasn't really on the table because if my
notion of productivity depended on me
like every day being able to just like
hammer on a bunch of stuff I'm very busy
I have lots of commitments what would
happen if I couldn't sleep I wouldn't be
able to do that so it I drifted
naturally towards a definition of
productivity which was it doesn't really
matter if you work tomorrow but it is
important that like this month you work
like writing a book it doesn't matter if
you work on your book chapter tomorrow
in particular but like this month you
have to spend a lot of time working on
it so it was uh like an insomnia
compatible definition of productivity
was sort of morphed into this idea of
slow productivity taking your your time
with it so it's interesting so like
sleep issues really shaped the way I
thought about work and put me on these
much longer time scales of productivity
try not to be dependent on any
particular day being critical to what
you do I don't want the high stress
situation I don't want the like I'm just
going to 10 hours a day for the next 10
days we're going to make this deal
happen like I can't operate in that
space because I worry about it anytime
my brain could betray me and I could
like lose sleep for a couple days I
think it's really important that you're
sharing this because while people's
challenges differ I think often times
people hear the content of my podcast or
other podcasts and think oh gosh I have
to have everything dialed in just right
when in fact most all of the tools and
protocols that have been discussed on
the huberman Lab podcast are in response
to a particular challenge that I've had
um or that others close to me have had
um and I I love this well I I'm sorry
that you suffer from insomnia U we have
a series uh on sleep with Matt Walker in
which he lays out some some great tools
that we haven't yet discussed on the
podcast I'll just um send you I'll text
you I'll call you with with a short list
of those and hopefully they'll help but
as we do cover insomnia in some depth
but but I think it's important that
people realize that they can be very
productive with the hours that they have
and the the moments or hours of of high
focus Clarity that they have um even if
they're not sleeping great even if
they're raising small children um
because that's the real world and
certainly that's the real world of
deadlines and Academia but um family and
um colds and flu and travel and jet lag
and arguments and all the happy stuff
too Vacations so um sounds like you're
very good at adapting your day to what's
going on around it but that you have
certain sort of committed time um am I
correct in assuming that you have at
least one period of say
60 to 90 minutes of real what you would
call Deep work uh let's say at least 5
days a week I know that might be an
underestimate but seems like that's what
what I'm that's what I'm extracting from
this that's the goal right so so to me
uh depending on the season is how
extreme that I can get so the the
busiest season would be like a teaching
semester right but even then I'm going
to make sure that five days a week I'm
starting with deep work and the
non-teaching days are more than the
teaching days compare that to the summer
for example where like all I do for the
most part is deep work no meetings on
Mondays and Fridays all admin stuff is
uh midday to early afternoon Tuesday
Wednesday Thursday um everything else is
deep work you know just locked in you
hours at a time but I want if I'm not
getting five days five days of starting
the day with deep work I'm I'm unhappy
right because I mean I keep coming back
to this is okay because I'm not going to
be able to I mean fortunately the
insomnia doesn't bother hasn't bothered
me in years but the the the threat of it
like completely shaped the way I I think
about things and because I know I'm
never going to be uh have a sort of like
an Elon mus style energy of like I can
just take on seven companies and make it
happen right I just don't have that
ability um I've always focused on the
long game and to me the long game plays
out with get your deep work time in you
know just keep working on the stuff you
do best and get better at it you know
tomorrow doesn't matter but if you if
you're doing this most days for the next
four months like that's going to matter
you know and so I often think about
productivity in my own life at the scale
of decades what do I want to do in my 20
you know okay what do I want to do in my
30s you know what do I want to do in my
40s you know U and that helps like in my
30s I had a lot of young kids like it's
yeah I mean the amount of time I could
spend total working is like much less
right but I could still think about what
do I want to do in my 30s how do I make
that happen let me make sure I'm pushing
like on those things then everything
else I can adapt to I can give here and
there you know it allows you to be very
adaptable when you're thinking about
what do I want to do you know for the
next 10 years it also means you're not
on a random Tuesday try yourself because
like why didn't I get three more hours
of working that becomes sort of a
nonsensical question when what you care
about is like what happens in the next
decade which is that's the long game
it's not about you know hustling today
it's about I came back to deep Ork day
after day after day when other people
got distracted by Tik Tok you know like
I'm GNA you whatever it's that coming
back to what matters again and again
thank you for tuning in to the huberman
lab Clips Channel if you enjoyed the
clip that you just viewed please check
out the full length Episode by clicking
here